# Christophe Dominik

Theodor-Lieser-Strasse 4, 06120 Halle, Germany

🗷 christophe.dominik@ufz.de | 🏕 Homepage | 🞓 Google Scholar | 🖪 ResearchGate | 🕦 Publons | 💆 Twitter |

10.11.1985 | French nationality





### Summary \_

Practical experience in landscape ecology, agroecology, and community ecology. 10+ years of experience in geographical information systems (GIS) and statistical software (R). 5+ years of experience in fieldwork and arthropods identification. 1+ year of work experience abroad (Philippines). Strong interests in landscape ecology, macroecology, pollination services, biological control, community ecology, gut microbiome, and data visualization.



### Education

### **Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg**

Dr. rer. nat. | Magna Cum Laude

Halle (Saale), Germany

Université de La Réunion Saint-Denis, Réunion Island

MASTER OF SCIENCE IN BIODIVERSITY AND TROPICAL ECOSYSTEMS

Nancy, France

Université Henri-Poincaré (UHP Nancy-1)

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN BIOLOGY OF ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS

2009



### **Research Experience**

### Helmholtz-Zentrum für Umweltforschung (UFZ)

Halle (Saale), Germany

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER | DEPARTMENT OF COMMUNITY ECOLOGY (BZF)

Jan. 2019 - present

P.I.: Schweiger O. | Main projects: PoshBee, VOODOO, INTERCEDE, iNTERACT, Safeguard, MAMBO, RestPoll, WildPosh, ANTENNA

- Mapping and classification of > 200 study sites using ArcGIS Pro.
- Fieldwork including nectar/haemolymph extraction, pollinator sampling, beekeeping activities, bumblebee experiments, pitfall traps.
- P.I. of three third-party funded projects iNTERACT, iPATHOS, iPATHOTELS.
- Co-P.I. and WP leader of the INTERCEDE project.
- · Project budget management.
- · Supervision of PhD students, Master students, and scientific staff.

### Helmholtz-Zentrum für Umweltforschung (UFZ)

Leipzig, Germany

PHD STUDENT/GUEST SCIENTIST | DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTATIONAL LANDSCAPE ECOLOGY (CLE)

Jul. 2012 - Dec. 2018

PhD Thesis: The effects of landscape heterogeneity on arthropod communities in rice agro-ecosystems. Supervisors: Seppelt R. and Václavík T. | Magna Cum Laude | Main project: LEGATO

• Mapping and classification of 30 study sites using ArcGIS 10.

GUEST SCIENTIST | CROP AND ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCES DIVISION (CESD)

- Landscape heterogeneity quantification via the calculation of landscape metrics (Fragstats).
- · Supervision of technical staff.

### International Rice Research Institute (IRRI)

Los Baños Laguna, Philippines

Jun. 2013 - Sep. 2014

Advisor: Horgan F.G. | Main project: LEGATO

- Sampling and arthropod identification (~ 80000 individuals) to morphospecies level (~ 200 morphospecies).
- Supervision of fieldwork assistants in the mountainous region of the Philippines.

### Centre national de la recherche scientifique (CNRS)

Nantes, France

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | LITTORAL, ENVIRONNEMENT, GÉOMATIQUE, TÉLÉDÉTECTION (UMR LETG)

Mar. 2012 - Jun. 2012

Supervisor: Godet L. | Main project: ECOSAL ATLANTIS

- Bird counts of common European passerine birds in salinas during a two weeks period.
- Mapping of the salinas located in Ré Island using ArcView 3.1 and calculation of landscape metrics (Fragstats).

### Centre national de la recherche scientifique (CNRS)

Nantes, France

Undergraduate Research student | Littoral, Environnement, Géomatique, Télédétection (UMR LETG)

Feb. 2011 - Jun. 2011

M.Sc. Thesis: Influence des structures spatiales sur la distribution des oiseaux terrestres dans un paysage fragmenté: cas des marais salants de Guérande.

Supervisor: Godet L. | M.Sc.2 Thesis grade: 16.67/20 Rank: 2/17 | Main project: ECOSAL ATLANTIS

· Methods and analyses similar to the research experience carried out in 2012 at the CNRS (see above).

## Centre de coopération internationale en recherche agronomique pour le développement (CIRAD)

Saint-Pierre, Réunion Island

 ${\tt Undergraduate\ Research\ student\ |\ Peuplements\ v\'eg\'etaux\ et\ bio-agresseurs\ en\ milieu\ tropical\ (UMR\ PVBMT)}$ 

Jan. 2010 - Jun. 2010

Supervisor: Quilici S. | M.Sc.1 Thesis grade: 15.73/20 Rank: 5/35

- Semi-field experiments: Infestation of four plant species within the Rosacea family with 40 larvae of Cibdela janthina.
- Daily survival monitoring and GLM analysis to test the food specificity of C.janthina on Rosacea plants.



### **Presentations**

### **INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCES**

SFE GFÖ EEE - Joint meeting, International Conference on Ecological Sciences

Metz, France

**DOMINIK C.**, WOGRAM S., MICHALSKI S., SCHWEIGER O.

Nov. 2022

Talk: Pollen limitation, local resource availability and pollinator community composition affect the fertilization success of Scabiosa ochroleuca.

SCAPE - Scandinavian Association of Pollination Ecology - Annual Meeting

Höör, Sweden

Papanikolaou A.D., Kühn I., Frenzel M., ..., Potts S.G., Roberts S.P.M., Schweiger O.

Oct. 2019

**Poster:** Wild bee and floral diversity co-vary in response to the direct and indirect impacts of land use.

**GfÖ -** Ecological Society of Germany, Austria, and Switzerland - Annual Meeting

Vienna, Austria Sep. 2018

**DOMINIK C.**, HORGAN F.G., SETTELE J., SEPPELT R., VÁCLAVÍK T.

. .

**Talk:** Landscape composition, configuration, and trophic interactions shape arthropod communities in rice agro-ecosystems.

GfÖ - Ecological Society of Germany, Austria, and Switzerland - Annual Meeting

Göttingen, Germany

**DOMINIK C.**, VÁCLAVÍK T., HORGAN F.G., SETTELE J., SEPPELT R.

Sep. 2015

Talk: Effects of landscape structures on rice agroecosystem biodiversity and biological control across the Philippines.

**FONA -** Sustainable Land Management - Status Conference

Berlin, Germany

DOMINIK C., VÁCLAVÍK T., HORGAN F.G., SETTELE J., SEPPELT R.

Apr. 2013

**Talk:** The effects of landscape heterogeneity on the biocontrol-production function in the rice dominated agroecosystems.

### PROJECT'S ANNUAL GENERAL MEETINGS (AGM)

Safeguard - AGM 2024DOMINIK C., MICHALSKI S., & SCHWEIGER O.Feb. 2024

PoshBee - AGM 2023 Rome, Italy

DOMINIK C., WUBET T. & Schweiger O.

Mar. 2023

Safeguard - AGM 2023 Sofia, Bulgaria

DOMINIK C., MICHALSKI S., & SCHWEIGER O.

Mar. 2023

Safeguard - AGM 2022 Online

DOMINIK C., MICHALSKI S., & SCHWEIGER O.

Jan. 2022

PoshBee - AGM 2021 Online

DOMINIK C., & Schweiger O. Jan. 2021

PoshBee - AGM 2020 Marseille, France

DOMINIK C., & Schweiger O.

Jan. 2020

**LEGATO - AGM 2016**Banaue, Philippines

**DOMINIK C.**, HORGAN F.G., SETTELE J., SEPPELT R., VÁCLAVÍK T.

Aug. 2016

**LEGATO - AGM 2015** Yogyakarta, Indonesia

DOMINIK C., VÁCLAVÍK T., HORGAN F.G., SETTELE J., SEPPELT R.

Mar. 2015

LEGATO - AGM 2013 Hanoi, Vietnam

**DOMINIK C.,** VÁCLAVÍK T., HORGAN F.G., SETTELE J., SEPPELT R.

Feb. 2013

### Research Grants, Funding, and Prize

### **RESEARCH GRANTS AND FUNDING**

**Total funding acquired:** 50.6k EUR

iDiv Flexpool Support Fund call	7.5k EUR
Consumables for pathogen screening, iPATHOTELS project   P.I.	2024
iDiv Flexpool Support Fund call	10k EUR
Consumables for pathogen screening, iPathos project   P.I.	2023
Helmholtz-Zentrum für Umweltforschung (UFZ) TB Support Fund	8k EUR
Consumables for gut microbiome analyses   P.I.	2022
Helmholtz-Zentrum für Umweltforschung (UFZ) TB Support Fund	9.6k EUR
Personnel (HiWi & Research assistant)   Co-P.I.	2022
iDiv Flexpool Support Fund call	10k EUR
Consumables for gut microbiome, pathogen & imaging flow cytometry analyses, iNTERACT project   P.I.	2021
Helmholtz-Zentrum für Umweltforschung (UFZ) TB Support Fund	5k EUR
Consumables for gut microbiome, pathogen & imaging flow cytometry analyses, iNTERACT project   P.I.	2021
Helmholtz-Zentrum für Umweltforschung (UFZ) TB PhD consortium	Three PhD positions
INTERCEDE PROJECT   CO-P.I. AND WP LEADER	2019
HIGRADE funding	500 EUR
EXTERNAL COURSE AND TRAVEL COSTS	2014

### **PRIZE**

Helmholtz-Zentrum für Umweltforschung (UFZ)2k EURPerformance bonus for special achievements2022

### Professional Activities and Memberships \_\_\_\_\_\_

RESEARCH PROJECTS	
☐ ANTENNA: Making technology work for monitoring pollinators  INVOLVED SCIENTIST	Biodiversa+ 2024 - present
WildPosh: Pan-European assessment, monitoring, and mitigation of chemical stressors on the health of wild pollinators	Horizon Europe
RestPoll: Restoring Pollinator habitats across European agricultural landscapes based on multi-actor participatory approaches  INVOLVED SCIENTIST	Horizon Europe 2023 - present
MAMBO: Modern approaches to the monitoring of biodiversity  INVOLVED SCIENTIST	Horizon Europe 2022 - present
☑ Safeguard: Safeguarding European wild pollinators INVOLVED SCIENTIST	Horizon 2020 2021 - present
<b>INTERACT</b> : Impacts of landscape structure, floral resources, and land-use intensity on the health of beneficial arthropods in agroecosystems  PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR	iDiv and UFZ support funds
☑ INTERCEDE: Interactions of farmland biodiversity and agricultural ecosystem services under climate change	UFZ
Co-P.I. and WP Leader	2020 - 2023
✓ VOODOO: Viral eco-evolutionary dynamics of wild and domestic pollinators under global change INVOLVED SCIENTIST	BiodivERsA 2020 - 2023

*Horizon 2020* 2019 - 2023

**BMBF** 

2011 - 2016

opportunities in irrigated rice based production systems

INVOLVED SCIENTIST, PHD STUDENT

**☑ PoshBee**: Pan-European assessment, monitoring, and mitigation of stressors on the health of bees

**LEGATO**: Land-use intensity and ecological engineering - Assessment tools for risks and

ECOSAL-ATLANTIS: Ecotourism in the Atlantic salt-marshes: a strategy for integral and sustainable development

INVOLVED UNDERGRADUATE, MASTER STUDENT

**INTERREG** 2007 - 2013

Feb. 2023

Nov. 2022

The Applied Ecologist's Blog

### **ORGANISATION ACTIVITIES**

CONFERENCES

- ANTENNA (Biodiversa+) Kick-off meeting 2024 Leipzig, Germany Mar. 2024

CO-ORGANISER

- GfÖ Annual Meeting 2023: Biodiversity monitoring using digital methods and artificial intelligence: Leipzig, Germany

shared challenges and opportunities

SESSION CO-CHAIR Sep. 2023

**WORKSHOPS** 

- Safeguard project (Horizon 2020) synthesis workshop Leipzig, Germany

CO-ORGANISER

- UFZ TB1-IP1 PhD Day Leipzig, Germany

CO-ORGANISER

**EVENTS** 

- Lange Nacht der Wissenschaften Halle, Germany

Jul. 2019, 2022 CO-ORGANISER

#### **PEER-REVIEWS**

**Journals** N = 37 completed reviews of 26 manuscripts

Landscape Ecology (12), Agriculture Ecosystems & Environment (7), Paddy and Water Environment (3), Journal of Applied Ecology (3), Ecology and Evolution (2), BMC Ecology (2), Basic and Applied Ecology (2), Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B (2), Environmental Research Letters (1), Journal of Insect Conservation (1), Insects (1), Scientific Reports (1).

Proposals iDiv Flexpool (3).

Theses Master (4), Bachelor (1).

### PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

iDiv associate member (**iDiv**), Gesellschaft für Ökologie (**GfÖ**).

### Professional Outreach

### MEDIA INTERVIEWS

Viren bedrohen die Welt der Insekten MDR Sachsen ☑ LINK TO THE ARTICLE Jul. 2020

### **PRESS & BLOGS**

Bees are still being harmed despite tightened pesticide regulations ScienceDaily ☑ LINK TO THE ARTICLE Nov. 2023

Better many small than a few large: how landscape configuration affects arthropod communities in rice agroecosystems

☑ LINK TO THE ARTICLE Aug. 2018

### **Professional Supervision**

### **PHD STUDENTS**

Hamilton Murray, Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Germany Co-supervisor 2024 - present MODERN TECHNOLOGIES FOR BUMBLE BEE MONITORING

Wogram Simon, Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Germany Co-supervisor 2023 - present

MODERN TECHNOLOGIES FOR POLLINATOR MONITORING

Heuschele Jonna, Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Germany Main supervisor 2020 - present

THE EFFECTS OF LANDSCAPE HETEROGENEITY AND CROP DIVERSITY ON BIOLOGICAL PEST CONTROL AND POLLINATOR HEALTH

**Liu Yicong,** Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Germany

Co-supervisor

POLLINATOR-PLANTS TRAIT MATCHING; POLLEN AND NECTAR QUALITY; LANDUSE EFFECTS ON NETWORKS RESILIENCE

#### MASTER STUDENTS

**Feldmann Noah,** Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Germany

Main supervisor

2023 - 2024

2020 - present

EFFECTS OF TRAFFIC, FLORAL RESOURCES, AND LANDSCAPE STRUCTURE ON POLLINATOR COMMUNITIES

LINK TO THE PDF

Wogram Simon, Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Germany | Main supervisor 2022 - 2023

Drivers of Pollen Limitation in *Scabiosa ochroleuca*: Relative importance of environmental factors at local, site

AND LANDSCAPE SCALES

LINK TO THE PDF

**Leyrer Dorothea,** Friedrich Wilhelm University of Bonn, Germany

Main supervisor

2021 - 2022

The effects of landscape structure, floral resources and land-use intensity on the foraging behaviour and

COLONY PERFORMANCE OF BUMBLEBEES

LINK TO THE PDF

Slivensky-Graf Cassidy, University of Bremen, Germany

Main supervisor

2021 - 2024

The effects of landscape structure and land-use intensity on the gut bacterial communities of *Poecilus* 

cupreus and Anchomenus dorsalis (Coleoptera: Carabidae)

LINK TO THE PDF

### **BACHELOR STUDENTS**

**Priese Carlotta,** Weihenstephan-Triesdorf University, Germany

Co-supervisor

2020 - 2021

### Professional Skills

**General:** Experience in leading and managing interdisciplinary projects, and in supervising staff, doctoral and master students.

Practical experience in experimental design, field sampling, and statistical analyses.

**Software:** R, ArcGIS 3.1/9/10/Pro, Fragstats, Adobe CS5, Markdown, GitHub.

Statistical analyses: ANOVA, LM/LME/GLS/GLM/GLMM, dissimilarity matrices, RLQ, 4th-corner, SEM.

**Sampling methods:** Sweep-net, suction sampler (blow-vac), capture-mark-recapture, pitfall traps, color plates, exclusion nets, point counts.

Pollinators: Pollinator-plant networks, camera trapping, haemolymph/nectar extraction, colony performance and fitness assessment.

Bumblebee colony performance and set-up, pollen collection.

Fauna identification: Tropical Asian rice-arthropods, European arthropods: hemipteran, heteropteran, lepidopteran, bombus.

European passerine birds, tropical passerine birds (La Réunion Island).

Languages: French (Mother tongue), English (Proficient), German (B1).

### Publications \_

### **PEER-REVIEW ARTICLES**

First author: 5/17 (30 %)
Corresponding author: 12/17 (70 %)

- † These authors contributed equally to the manuscript
- [17] Liu Y., Dunker S., Durka W., Dominik C., ..., & Schweiger O. (2024). Eco-evolutionary processes shaping floral nectar sugar composition. Scientific Reports 14, 13856.

https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-64755-5

[16] Sponsler D., **Dominik C.**, Biegerl C., Honchar H., Schweiger O. & Steffan-Dewenter I. (2024). High rates of nectar depletion in summer grasslands indicate competitive conditions for pollinators. **Oikos** e10495.

https://doi.org/10.1111/oik.10495

[15] Maurer C., Martínez-Núñez C., **Dominik C.**, ..., & Albrecht M. (2024). Landscape simplification leads to loss of plant-pollinator interaction diversity and flower visitation frequency despite buffering by abundant generalist pollinators. **Diversity and Distributions**, 00, e13853. http://doi.org/10.1111/ddi.13853

- [14] Askri D., Pottier M., Arafah K., ..., **Dominik C.**, ..., & Bulet P. (2024). A blood test to monitor bee health across a European network of agricultural sites of different land-use by MALDI BeeTyping mass spectrometry. **Science of the Total Environment**, 172239. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.172239
- [13] Laurent M., Bougeard S., Caradec L., ..., **Dominik C.**, ..., & Chauzat M.P. (2024). Novel indices reveal that pollinator exposure to pesticides varies across biological compartments and crop surroundings. **Science of the Total Environment**, 927:172118. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.172118
- [12] Babin A., Schurr F., Delannoy S., ..., **Dominik C.**, ..., & Dubois E. (2024). Distribution of infectious and parasitic agents among three sentinel bee species across European agricultural landscapes. **Scientific Reports**, 14 (1), 3524. http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-53357-w
- [11] Nicholson C.<sup>†</sup>, Knapp J.<sup>†</sup>, Kiljanek T., ..., **Dominik C.**, ..., & Rundlöf M. **(2024)**. Agricultural pesticide use negatively affects bumblebee colonies across Europe. **Nature**, 1-4. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06773-3
- [10] Høye T.T., August T., Banzan Mario V., ..., **Dominik C.**, ..., & Stowell S. **(2023)**. Modern Approaches to the Monitoring of Biodiversity (MAMBO). **Research Ideas and Outcomes**, 9: e116951. https://doi.org/10.3897/rio.9.e116951
- [9] Bottero I.<sup>†</sup>, **Dominik C.**<sup>†</sup>, Schweiger O.<sup>†</sup>, ..., & Stout J. **(2023)**. Impact of landscape configuration and composition on pollinator communities across different European biogeographic regions. **Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution**, 11:309. https://doi.org/10.3389/fevo.2023.1128228
- [8] Hodge S., Schweiger O., Klein A.M., ..., Dominik C., ..., & Stout J. (2022). Design and planning of a transdisciplinary investigation into farmland pollinators: rationale, co-design, and lessons learned. Sustainability, 14(17), 10549. https://doi.org/10.3390/su141710549
- [7] Gérard M., Baird E., Breeze T., Dominik C., & Michez D. (2022). Impact of crop exposure and agricultural intensification on the phenotypic variation of bees. Agriculture, Ecosystems & Environment, 338. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agee.2022.108107
- [6] Dominik C., Seppelt R., Horgan F.G., Settele J., & Václavík T. (2022). Landscape heterogeneity filters functional traits of rice arthropods in tropical agroecosystems. Ecological Applications, e2560. https://doi.org/10.1002/eap.2560
- [5] Vanderplanck M., Michez D., Albrecht M., ..., Dominik C., ..., & Gérard M. (2021). Monitoring bee health in European agro-ecosystems using wing morphology and fat bodies. One Ecosystem 6: e63653. https://doi.org/10.3897/oneeco.6.e63653
- [4] Settele J., Heong K.L., Kühn I., ..., Dominik C., ..., & Wiemers M. (2018). Rice Ecosystem Services in South-East Asia. Paddy and Water Environment, 16: 211-214. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10333-018-0656-9
- [3] **Dominik C.**, Seppelt R., Horgan F.G., Settele J., & Václavík T. **(2018)**. Landscape composition, configuration, and trophic interactions shape arthopod communities in rice agro-ecosystems. **Journal of Applied Ecology**, 55: 2461-2472. https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2664.13226
- [2] Dominik C., Seppelt, R., Horgan F.G., Marquez L., Settele J., & Václavík T. (2017). Regional-scale effects override the influence of fine-scale landscape heterogeneity on rice arthropod communities. Agriculture, Ecosystems & Environment, 246: 269–278. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agee.2017.06.011
- [1] **Dominik C.**, Ménanteau L., Chadenas C., & Godet L. **(2012)**. The influence of salina landscape structures on terrestrial bird distribution in the Guérande basin (Northwestern France). **Bird Study**, 59: 483- 495. https://doi.org/10.1080/00063657.2012.715279

### IN REVIEW/PREPARATION

- [7] Wyver C. et al. (in preparation)
- [6] Lanuza J.B. et al. (in preparation)
- [5] Tourbez C. et al. (in preparation)
- [4] Heuschele J. et al. (in preparation)
- [3] Dominik C. et al. (in preparation)
- [2] Radermacher N. et al. (in preparation)
- [1] Dietenberger M. et al. (in preparation)

### **THESES**

- [2] **Dominik C. (2019)**. The effects of landscape heterogeneity on arthropod communities in rice agro-ecosystems. Doctoral Thesis, Martin-Luther-Universität Halle-Wittenberg.
  - Link to the PDF http://dx.doi.org/10.25673/13861
- [1] **Dominik C. (2011)**. Influence des structures spatiales des marais salants sur les communautés d'oiseaux terrestres. Master Thesis, Université de La Réunion.
  - Link to the PDF